Guide to the Russell Henry Chittenden Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Russell Henry Chittenden papers
1870-1945
MS 611
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
(4 boxes, 1 folio)
Correspondence, writings and memorabilia almost entirely relating to Chittenden's work as a physiologist and expert on nutrition. Also essays documenting his part in the development at Yale University of the Sheffield Scientific School, which he directed from 1898 to 1922. Important correspondents are Willy Kühne, his professor at the University of Heidelberg, and Ira Remsen, chairman of the Referee Board of Consulting Scientific Experts of the Department of Agriculture, of which Chittenden was a member from 1908 to 1914. Also in the papers are the manuscripts of his autobiography (written in 1936), miscellaneous family papers, diplomas and awards.
Chittenden, R. H. (Russell Henry), 1856-1943
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Russell H. Chittenden, 1944.
Existence and Location of Copies
Autobiography of Russell Henry Chittendenis available on microfilm (274 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM6.
Scope and Contents
The Russell H. Chittenden Papers, which span the years 1870 to 1945, include correspondence, writings, and miscellaneous files. The papers are largely professional, reflecting Chittenden's training in physiological chemistry and his interest in problems of nutrition.
The correspondence files (1870-1941) contain both personal and professional correspondence, although the bulk of the material is professional. From 1879 to 1893 Wilhelm Kühne, a German physiologist, was a major correspondent. In 1875 he had read a paper by Chittenden and in 1878 invited him to be his student and lecture assistant at the University of Heidelberg. In 1880, a year after his return from Germany, Chittenden was awarded the Ph.D. and two years later was appointed professor of physiological chemistry in the Sheffield Scientific School at Yale University. Shortly thereafter he became a member of the governing board of the school and its permanent secretary. From 1908 to 1914 Chittenden served on the referee board of consulting scientific experts to the Secretary of Agriculture, a forerunner of today's Food and Drug Administration. There is a good deal of correspondence with Ira Remsen, a chemist who was chairman of this board, regarding experiments and findings, as well as briefs, minutes, and reports on the work of the board.
Chittenden's writings span the years 1898 to 1945 and include drafts of scientific papers, speeches, and an extensive autobiography (Box 2, folders 35-37). Dated writings are arranged in chronological order. Undated writings are divided into two alphabetical sections, each representing a major interest: nutrition and science, and the Sheffield Scientific School and education.
Among the miscellaneous files are notes and papers on chemistry and nutrition, and memorabilia from professional organizations. There are also many tributes and honors awarded to Chittenden.
The papers were donated by Russell H. Chittenden to Yale University in 1944. For related papers see the Records of the Sheffield Scientific School, 1846-1956, YRG 31.
Biographical / Historical
Physiological chemist; professor of physiological chemistry at Yale University 1882-1922; director of Sheffield Scientific School, Yale University, 1898-1922, and trustee 1900-1930; member of the Referee Board of the Department of Agriculture 1908-1915.
Food additives; Medicine; Nutrition; Science; World War, 1914-1918; Europe; Germany; Chemists; Physiologists; Beaumont, William, 1785-1853; Chittenden, R. H. (Russell Henry), 1856-1943; Kühne, W. (Willy), 1837-1900; Remsen, Ira, 1846-1927; Chittenden family; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Sheffield Scientific School
- Inventory, 1870-1945
  - Correspondence, personal, 1918 February-June (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence, personal: concerning The History of the Sheffield Scientific School, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, professional, 1870-1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 4-20)
  - Referee Board of Consulting Scientific Experts of the Department of Agriculture
    - Appointments, agreements, payroll, 1911-1912 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Briefs presented to the Board, 1909, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Minutes of Board meetings, 1908-1911 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Questions for the Board concerning sulpher dioxide, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Report: "An Experimental Study of the Effect of Aluminum Compounds, When Used in Foods, on the Nutrition and Health of Man", 1913 (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
    - Reports, 1908-1911, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Writings
    - "Economy in Nutrition", Circa 1904 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - "The Proposed Graduate Year for the Select Course in Preparation for Business", 1915 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - [Alumni?] address, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - "Research in Chemistry as Related to Medicine", [1922?] (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - no folder (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - "A Memorial to William Beaumont, M.D.", 1926 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - "Lafayette Benedict Mendel", Circa 1936 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - "Sixty Years of Service in Science: An. Autobiography", 1936 (Box 2, Folder 35-37)
    - "The Club", 1938 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - "Parsimony in Nutrition", Circa 1942 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - "The First Twenty-Five Years of the American Society of Biological Chemists", Circa 1945 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Writings on nutrition and science, undated (Box 3, Folder 41-58)
    - Writings on Sheffield Scientific School and education, undated (Box 3, Folder 59-71)
  - Writings of others, 1908-1923 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Miscellaneous files
    - Chemistry and nutrition papers
      - Chemistry notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 73)
      - Memoranda to the Saltpeter Commission, Circa (Box 4, Folder 74)
      - Minutes of the meeting of the Commission for the Study of Problems Relating to Human Nutrition, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 75)
      - Notes and charts on food and nutrition, Circa 1918 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Professional organizations
      - Membership certificates, 1880-1912 (Box 4, Folder 77)
      - Memento commemorating the founding of the American Physiological Society, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 78)
      - Lists of colleagues with list of books, undated (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Tributes and awards
      - Chittenden dinner: correspondence, addresses, ticket, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 80)
      - Guest book from luncheon arranged by Chittenden's former students, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 81)
      - Tribute album from the Governing Board of the Sheffield Scientific School, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 82)
      - Tributes and awards, 1878-1930 (Box 4, Folder 83)
      - Honorary diplomas
        General note
        See: Box 5
    - Family Papers
      - Family genealogy and personal history, undated (Box 4, Folder 84)
      - Legal papers, 1877-1912 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Reprints and newspaper clippings, 1909-1918, undated (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - Diplomas
    - Bachelor of Philosophy: Yale College, 1875 (Box 5)
    - Doctor of Philosophy: Yale College, 1880 (Box 5)
    - National Academy of Sciences of the United States, 1890 (Box 5)
    - New York Medical Legal Society, 1894 (Box 5)
    - American Philosophical Society, 1904 (Box 5)
    - Honorary Doctor of Science degree: University of Pennsylvania, 1904 (Box 5)
    - Honorary Doctor of Laws degree: Washington University (Missouri), 1915 (Box 5)
    - Yale Chapter, Society of Sigma XI, 1916 (Box 5)
    - Society of Medical and Natural Sciences (Brussells), 1919 (Box 5)
    - Honorary Doctor of Laws degree: Yale University, 1922 (Box 5)
    - New York Academy of Medicine, 1930 (Box 5)
    - Honorary Doctor of Medicine degree: Medical Society of Connecticut, 1934 (Box 5)